A Guide to the Papers of the Washington Family of Caroline County, Virginia 1800-1875
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Papers of the Washington Family of Caroline County, Virginia 1800-1875
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3683
This collection consists of ca. 500 manuscripts and 6 ledgers.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from Mr. and Mrs. George Washington of Woodford, Virginia on March 16, 1951.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of the Washington Family of Caroline County, including ca. 500 manuscripts and 6 ledgers, 1800-1875, consist of receipts, accounts, and deeds, with a few letters concerning financial matters. Mentioned in the papers are George Washington, [his widow] Elizabeth Washington, [their] children Anna, Selma, William, Dorthea, and Eliza; John Washington, his wife Anne, and their children George B. Walker, and John, Jr., and grandson Thomas Henry Purks; George Buckner and his brother Dr. Horace Buckner, John Vass and his daughter Ann Vass, Thomas Henry Burke and his daughter Susan, and William Taliaferro. Most of the papers are the financial records of Elizabeth, John, and William Washington and of Thomas Henry Burke. Included in the papers is the will of John Washington, 1850, and a deed, 1853, concerning a division of his property among his sons and grandsons.
The ledgers are: (1) John Washington's arithmetic example book, 1816; (2) his notebook of accounts with George Buckner, 1830-1847; (3) his farm account book, 1826-1876; (4) a ledger of accounts, 1823-1829, of Anna, Selma, Willliam, and Dorthea Washington with Elizabeth Washington, Jr., containing accounts of John Washington 1849, records of litigation and law notes taken at the University of Virginia, 1846-1848; (6) John Washington, Jr.'s commonplace and latin excercise book.
Items of special interest include: the folder containing William Washington's orations; a folder of early surveys of the Washington estate; and several documents relating to the purchase of new slaves and the retrieval of runaway slaves, which are located in the Legal and Correspondence folders. Scattered throughout the Bills, Receipts and Financial Records folders are references to the hiring out of slaves: see for example the list of bonds for the hire of Mrs. Sally Hill's negroes located in the 1938 financial folder.
Arrangement
The contents of the collection have been filed by subject, with financial records further subdivided into chronological folders. Financial items involving expenses over a period of years are filed under the earliest relevant year.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1823-1924 (Box 1)
- Surveys, Land Boundaries ca. 1796-1850 (Box 1)
- Wills, Estate Accounts, Related Legal Agreements 1813-1853 (Box 1)
- Legal Documents, Court Summonses, Pedigrees 1823-1840 (Box 1)
- Orations of William Washington ca. 1834 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records of the Washington Family 1775-1814 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Mrs. Buckner, Elizabeth Washington 1815-1819 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, Elizabeth Washington 1820 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Vass Brown, Thomas Henry Burke, Elizabeth Washington 1821 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: T. H. Burke, George Buckner, Vass Brown, Elizabeth Washington 1822 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, John Burke, John Vass, Elizabeth Washington 1823 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, Whitaker Campbell, E. Washington, Jn. Washington 1824 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, Mrs. Buckner, Elizabeth Washington, E.D. Withers 1825 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, John Vass, Dorthea, John, and Elizabeth Washington 1826 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, T.S. Courtney, Elizabeth, John, and William Washington 1827 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Henry Burke, John Vass, Elizabeth and William Washington 1828 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Susan Burke, William Purks, Ann Vass, John Vass, Elizabeth, John, and William Washington 1829 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: William Purks, Ann and John Vass, Thomas Walker, Elizabeth, John and William Washington 1830 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Edward, Henry, and George Burke, Elizabeth, John, and William Washington 1831 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: William Taliaferro, Elizabeth, John, and William Washington 1832 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Thomas Jones, Elizabeth, John, and William Washington 1833 (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: William Washington 1834 (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Joseph Fogg, John, and William Washington 1835 (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: John and William Washington 1836-1837, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: Sally Hill, John, and William Washington 1838 (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: John and William Washington 1839-1840, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records: William Washington 1841-1842, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Bills, Receipts and Financial Records after 1842 and n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellany 1830-1882 (Box 2)
- Edward Burke's Account Book 1830-1850, AMs (Box 2)
- Autograph Book [1847] (Box 2)
- John Washington, Jr.'s Latin excercise book 1868 (Box 2)
- Autograph book 1816 (Box 2)
- Autograph book 1823-1824 (Box 2)
- John Washington's Account Book 1823-1848, AD (Box 2)
- Survey map of 2400 acre property n.d.